嘿，伙计们，我叫TheCherno，欢迎回到我的游戏引擎系列
hey, what's up guys, my name is TheCherno, welcome back to my game engine series
所以就像昨天，我才下飞机，在欧洲呆了五个半星期，时差反应很严重
so I just got off a plane like yesterday, and I'm super jet lagged been in Europe for like the last five and a half weeks
所以这期视频有点乱，原谅我，但是我很累
so this video is kind of going to be a little bit all over the place, forgive me, but I'm very very tired
无论如何，欢迎回到我的游戏引擎系列，上期说了变换，如果你们还没看的话，就去看看吧
anyway, welcome back to my game engine series, last time we talked about transforms, check out that video if you haven't already
今天我要和你们说说材质了，我们要介绍一下材质，为什么它们会存在
and today I'm going to talk to you about materials, we're going to have a bit of an introduction to materials, why they exist
我们将如何使用它们，为什么我们在游戏引擎中需要它们
how we're going to use them, why we need them in game engines
我不会用图表之类的创作深入的视频了，我会保存它
I'm not going to make an in-depth video with like diagrams or anything, I'm going to save that
只要是关于材质和以后的任何东西，我向你们保证
and just have that be about materials and whatever in the future, I promise you guys that
我知道我之前说过，这将是一堆深入的视频
I know that I've said, it's going to be a bunch of in-depth videos
如果有人收集了深入的视频，我保证会制作，请顺便在评论区中发一下
If anyone has a collection of the in-depth videos, I promise to make, please post it in the comments by the way
因为我将像下周左右开始研究它们
because I'm going to start working on them like next week or so
但是我们将对什么是材质做一个基本的概述，我们将很快进入一个非常基本的材质系统
but we're just going to have a bit of a basic overview of what materials are, we're going to quickly jam in a very basic material system
甚至不是一个材质系统，只是为了让你们知道一切实际上是如何联系在一起的
not really even a material system, but just to kind of give you the idea of how everything ties together practically
今天就是那样的，然后我想下期我们可能会继续讲着色器或纹理
and that's going to be kind of it for today, and then I think next time we might continue on with shaders or textures
因为纹理也是我想做的事情，但是无论如何，先说说材质吧，比如为什么需要材质系统
because textures are also something that I want to get done, but anyway, let's talk about materials, like why do we need a material system
那么现在，让我先运行一下代码，看看做到哪儿了
so right now, let me just maybe launch our code, and we'll see what we actually have
好吧，我们已经绘制了这个三角形，并且能够旋转和移动
okay, so we had this triangle, and we were able to like rotate it and move it around
我猜我们基本上可以移动相机
and we basically could move the camera around I guess
然后还有一堆贴图，我们用单独的变换将它们渲染为单独的对象，上期也做了
And then we had like a bunch of tiles that we were rendering as separate objects with separate transforms as well we did last episode
因此假设想绘制其中一个三角形，或者比如其中一个正方形一样，因为决定绘制每个正方形
so suppose that we wanted to make one of those triangles, like I don't know, or like one of those squares as we kind of decide to draw each square
我们想让它们成为不同的颜色，那么那到底是如何做到的呢
we want to make them a different color, so how does that work exactly
到目前为止，我们知道着色器的存在，作为一种基本上告诉GPU如何处理得到的数据的方式
well so far we know that shaders exist, as a way to essentially tell our GPU what to do with data that it gets
我们实际上是如何意识到我们屏幕上的数据，对吧
how we actually realize I guess that data onto our screen, right
我们有顶点位置，我们有屏幕坐标之类的，我们需要绘制某些几何图形
we have vertex positions, we have you know our screen kind of coordinates or whatever, we need to draw certain geometry
我们会调用绘制指令DrawCall，实际上就比如把两个三角形组成一个正方形，对吧
we've given a draw command, a draw call to actually draw like say two triangles to make up like a square, right
我们已经有了所有的数据，但是我们如何实际绘制它，我们把什么放在屏幕上
we've got all that data, but how do we actually draw it, what do we put on the screen
顶点着色器负责处理那个，然后我们如何着色这些像素，这些像素是什么颜色的
vertex shader takes care of that, and then how do we shader those pixels, those pixels, what color do they amount to
片段着色器或像素着色器会处理那个，所以那就是着色器，就是个程序，它决定了所有
the fragment shader or the pixel shader deals with that, so that's what a shader is, it's a program, which determines all that
如果你们不太熟悉的话，就去看看OpenGL系列中的有关着色器的视频吧，应该在那个系列
and if you're kind of rusty on that, check out either my OpenGL series on shaders or the actual shaders, I think video in this series
因为那也很有用，所以着色器就是做那些的，对吧
because that was quite informative as well, that's what a shader does, right
所以那很棒，我们知道你们现在应该能做的是，如果我想想
so that's great, and we know that what you should be able to do right now is, if I see
将三角形设置为红色，你们应该能够进入着色器并实际更改代码，并使其输出红色
make the triangle red, you should be able to go into the shader and actually change the code and just make it output a flat red color
简单，对吧，因为现在是蓝色的，就会改变一些数字，突然这个着色器要输出红色
easy, right, because I'm putting blue, I'll change some numbers around, suddenly this shader is going to output red
我们甚至称它为blueShader，但在现实世界中，我们喜欢编写比那更灵活的着色器
and I think we even call this the blue shader, but in the real world, we like to write shaders that are a lot more flexible than that
你们不想只写个blueShader的着色器，那就完了，原因是着色器是，它就像程序，对吧
you don't want to just write a shader that's like your blue shader, and that's done, the reason is that shaders are, it's like a program, right
毕竟你们也不会写个只计算一个数字的程序
you wouldn't write a program which just calculates a single number
最好编写一个包含两个输入的程序，然后像将它们加在一起之类的，然后给你们答案
it would be much better to write a program which takes in two inputs, and then like adds them together or whatever, and then gives you your answer
那不是更有用吗，你们可以有个程序，计算10加5，对吧，就是那样
isn't that much more kind of useful, you could have a program, which computes 10 plus 5, right, and that's it
那就是你们的程序，太棒了，它居然可以计算10加5，太神奇了
that's your program, great, it can compute 10 plus 5, it's amazing
但是如果我要写个程序，要求用户输入两个数字，然后将它们加在一起，该怎么办
but what if I make a program which asks the user for two numbers and then adds them together
它实际上变得更强大，更有用，和着色器一样的道理，对吧
how much more powerful, how much more useful does that actually become, same deal with shaders, right
我们可以写一个只输出红色的着色器，完全可以
we could write a shader that just outputs red, totally fine
我们就叫它RedShader，已经有了个BlueShader，为什么没有RedShader
we could call it the RedShader, great, we've got a BlueShader, why not have a RedShader
但是，如果我可以创建一个着色器，将一些数据作为输入，然后输出该颜色，该怎么办
but what if I could make a shader that takes in some data as an input, and then outputs that color
我可以称那个着色器为平面颜色着色器，对吧
and I could call that shader the flat color shader, right
它要做的就是输入一个输入，可能是红色，可能是蓝色，可能是我能想到的任何颜色
and all it would do is take in an input, which might be red, might be blue, might be any color I can think of
然后把所有的像素都染成那种颜色，对吧，那会有用得多，那就是一种材质的来源
and then shades all the pixels to that color, right, that would be a lot more useful, wouldn't it, and that's kind of where a material comes in
因为我们要做的是尽可能灵活地编写着色器，对吧
because what we do is we write our shaders as flexible as possible, right
可能是由工程师或技术艺术家之类的人写的
might be written by like, you know, an engineer or a technical artist or something like that
然后所有其他正在制作游戏的艺术家，他们需要能够真正让游戏看起来不错
and then all the other artists, who are working on the game, who need to be able to actually make the game look good
也许科技艺术家也会进来，把数据输入现成的着色器，对吧
and maybe the tech artists as well, they're going to come in and feed data into that ready-made shader, right
他们不需要了解着色器，他们只知道它需要这些输入，输入可以是真正定义的任何东西
they don't have to know anything about the shader, they just know that it takes these inputs, and inputs could be anything really that define
那种材质，那种表面应该是什么样的，对吗
what that material, what that surface kind of should be like, right
所以那可能是任何颜色，可能是纹理
so that could be anything from like the color, could be like a texture
什么样的定义表面可以像其他表面属性一样，比如它有多粗糙或光滑，对吧
which to kind of defines the surface could be like other surface properties, such as how rough or smooth is it, right
是金属吗，是塑料吗，我们这里也有PBR，可能是法线映射，对吧
is it a metal, is it a plastic, we're kind of getting to PBR here as well, Um, could be a normal map, right
它只是定义了额外的细节，所以当我们进行光线计算时，它看起来比它详细得多
which just defines extra detail, so that when we do our lighting calculations, it looks like, it's a lot more detailed than it is
我们实际上可以做很多不同的事情
we have a lot of different things that we can actually do
还有其他东西也被使用，比如光线方向，相机方向，所有需要输入到着色器中的东西
there's other things that are used as well, like light direction, camera direction, all that stuff that's required to be input into the shader
尽管这种东西通常是由渲染器而不是由材质处理的，但你们也应该明白我的意思
although that kind of stuff is usually handled by the renderer and not by the material, but you kind of get my point
我们输入了很多东西，显然可以通过顶点属性输入
there's a lot of stuff that we kind of feed in, and obviously it could be fed in somewhat through the vertex attributes
那就是我们一直在做的事情
that's kind of what we've been doing in a way
比如你们知道的，我们用这个三角形的位置，来计算它的颜色，对吧
like for example, you know, we use the position of this triangle, I think, um, to actually work out its color, right
因为我们有不同的颜色，那就是，我不知道，那是一种颜色吗
cause we have a varying color and that is, I don't know, is that a color
我认为，在某种程度上，我认为对于三角形，我们只是将颜色计算为位置或类似的颜色
I think at some point, I think for the triangle, we were just calculating the color to be like positions or something like that
那就是，你们知道的，为位置取顶点属性，然后实际计算
that's done by just, you know, taking in the vertex attribute for the position and then actually calculating
你们知道的，哪个片段位于插值处，我们得到所有这些颜色
you know, which fragment lies where interpolating and we get all these colors
没关系，我们显然可以有一个顶点颜色，对吧
that's fine and all, and we could obviously have a vertex color, right
但那显然又是，被烘焙到数据中的东西，如果我想能够即时改变这种情况，对吧
but that obviously is again, something that's baked into data, what if I want to be able to change that kind of on the fly, right
那就是获得整个数据的地方，有堆数据，然后有个着色器，这些数据被称为统一变量，对吧
and that's where we get the whole data, having a bunch of data and then having a shader, and that data is called a uniform, right
我们有统一变量，基本上是我们可以在绘制之前将其传输到着色器的数据片段
we have uniforms, which is basically pieces of data that we can transmit to the shader at like before we draw
它是在每次绘制时完成的，对吧，然后那样，当决定实际绘制时，就需要实际找到数据
and it's done kind of per draw, right, and then that way, when we decide to actually draw something and it needs to actually find that data
你们可以从统一变量中访问数据，就那样，现在可以看到是红色的，它将是蓝色的
you can just access the data from the uniform, and that's it, we can now see that it's going to be red, it's going to be blue
所以那就是材质的本质
so that's what a material essentially is
就是个着色器，它定义了所有内容，它的代码说，这是我将要使用的算法
it's a shader, which defines how everything, it's the code that says, this is kind of the algorithm I'm going to use
这就是确定最终颜色的结果，但它需要输入，这些输入被称为统一变量
this is what's going to happen to determine that final color, but it needs inputs, and those inputs are called uniforms
那就是材质，是一堆统一变量，着色器和数据，就是那样
and that's what a material is, it's a bunch of uniforms and a shader Shader and data, that's all it is
在我见过的每个游戏引擎中，它几乎都是这样的，它总是一个着色器和一堆统一变量
and it's pretty much that way in every game engine that I've ever seen, it's always a shader and a bunch of uniforms
正如我所说，我们可能会在一段深入视频中看到一个更技术性的概述
and we might take a look at a more technical overview of that, as I said, in an in-depth video
但本质上，我只是想让你们记住，那就是全部
but essentially I'm just trying to put into your heads that, that's really all it is
显然，这些系统的复杂性可能是巨大的，因为即使我们确实希望着色器具有灵活性
obviously the complexity of these systems can be enormous, because even though we do want our shader to be flexible
就像我说的，我们不希望它变得灵活到非常慢，像一堆检查一样，如果要检查我们想要的
as I said, we don't want it to be flexible to the point of being very slow and doing like a bunch of if checks to check is this what we want
因为你们本质上可以创建一个超级着色器，包含了所有可能的东西，对吧
because you can make an uber shader essentially, which is like just every possible thing, right
你们可以为游戏创建一个着色器，那就是所有的可能性，对吧，但那有点，相当糟糕的
you can have one shader for your whole game, and that's all of the possibilities, right, but that's somewhat, that's pretty bad
就像你们不想那样，所以在现实世界中最终发生的是一个聪明的
like you don't want that, and so what ends up happening in the real world is an intelligent
就像你们编写的着色器编译器一样，它将基本上通过着色器并确定实际需要什么
like shader compiler that you've written will essentially go through the shader and determine what is actually needed
然后抓取所需内容的所有不同构建块，将其组合成一个着色器
and then kind of grab all the different building blocks of the stuff that's needed, combine that into a shader
然后将其创建为着色器，因此最终会有300个着色器，而不是一个会做300个操作的着色器
and then just create that as a shader, so instead of having one shader that can do 300 things, you end up having 300 shaders
即使你们写了一个，也要稍后再讨论，因为我们肯定会在将来的某个时候添加那样的系统
even though you wrote one, so more on that later, because we're definitely going to add a system like that sometime in the future
这很有用，但是无论如何，我不想坐在这里聊几个小时
it's very useful, but anyway, I don't want to sit here talking for hours
我绝对可以，特别是因为我有点炸，但我想直接去写一些像这样的东西
I definitely could, especially because my mind is a bit fried, but I want to get in and basically write something like this
但是我们的目标是尝试用不同的颜色创建其中一些正方形
but our goal is going to be to try and make some of these squares in different colors
我们将通过创建材质，然后提交材质来实现那个
and we're going to do that by making a material, and then kind of submitting that material
除了我们实际提交的几何
alongside our geometry that we actually submit
然后通常会发生的是，如果你们有个网格或模型类
and then usually what would happen is, if you have like a mesh or a model class, essentially
其中包含你们实际渲染的所有几何图形，通常也具有与之相关的材质
which contains all of your geometry that you actually render, that also usually has materials associated with it
因为很明显，如果你们看看游戏引擎
because obviously if you kind of look at a game engine
在某种程度上就是在写你们的资产，从来没有处理到这个级别的代码
you kind of author your assets in a way that you're never dealing with code to this level, usually,
除非你们喜欢实验或搞东西
unless you're like experimenting or playing around with stuff
通常，艺术家会创建3D模型，他们显然想在某种工具中对其应用材质
usually artists will kind of make a 3D model, and they obviously want to apply a material to it in some sort of tool
所以这个模型和那个材质是联系在一起的，对吧
and so that model gets linked with that material, right
因为如果你们把材质与几何分开，就很奇怪，但是通常情况并非如此
because it would be very weird if you kind of like, yes, you can have materials separate to geometry, but usually that's not the case
我是说，想想看，如果建造这个房间，你们想在游戏引擎中渲染它，这是张木桌，对吧
I mean, think about it, if you're building this room and you want to render it in your game engine, this is a wooden table, right
你们可以为木桌创建几何，然后把木质材质应用于其中
you make the geometry for the wooden table, and then you apply the wooden material to it
你们永远不会想把它们分开，因为那就是事实，对吧
you would never want to separate them, because that's just the way that this is, right
我的意思是如果你们正在建造真正动态的东西，材质可能会随着时间的推移而退化或改变
I mean, if you're building really dynamic stuff, the material might degrade or change over time
总是有例外，但想法是我们想要个网格，并且有个材质，所以通常这两个是绑在一起的
there are always exceptions, but the idea is that we want a mesh, and we have a material with it, so usually those two pieces are tied together
所以不会真的只是在那里写个材质，然后编码，绝对可以实现那个，我们肯定会支持
so you wouldn't really just author a material right there and then encode, definitely can do that, we definitely will support that
但我只是想向你们展示我是否真的在用Hazel创作游戏的更大背景，或者在引擎中
but I'm just trying to show you kind of the bigger picture of if I was actually building a game with Hazel, or with an engine
那个的运行原理，无论如何，我们将深入研究一下这段代码
how would that work, anyway, we're going to go in and just literally play around with this code a little bit
这将更像是一个自由式视频，我只是在讨论我在做什么
this is going to be kind of more of a freestyle video where I just kind of just discuss what I'm doing so much
我们并没有真正写最后的代码，但就只是像在谈论概念
and we're not really writing final code, but we're just like talking about concepts
玩一下，实现一些系统
and playing around with them, and implementing somewhat of a system
但是从本质上讲，如果我们只是考虑我们需要什么，那么我们需要一个材质类
but essentially, if we just kind of think about what we need, so we need a material class
或者保存着色器的，那就是我们编译的着色器程序，然后需要些方法来为它定义数据
or something which holds a shader, which again is our compiled kind of shader program, and then we need some way to define data for it
现在再说一次，这个系统通常会变得非常复杂，因为我们定义的数据
now again, this system ends up being really complicated usually, because the data that we define
比如说，我们定义了什么数据，如何正确设置统一变量，如果统一变量不存在会发生什么
like what to say, what data we define, how do we set uniforms properly, what happens if the uniform doesn't exist
我们是否需要首先实际检查着色器代码，用来查看实际存在哪些统一变量
do we need to actually check the shader code first to see what uniforms even exist
所以那些是我们唯一可以设置的，然后还需要接受几乎任何类型的数据
so those are the only ones that we can set, and then we also need to accept pretty much any kind of data
然后我们如何统一变量或直接访问常量缓冲区接口，对吧
and then how do we interface with uniform buffers or direct access constant buffers, right
在这里，我们通常不是一个接一个地提交统一变量，而是提交一个常量缓冲区
where instead of submitting uniforms one by one, we usually submit a constant buffer
我们可能有多个常量缓冲区，因为一个可能由渲染提交，或者一个可能由材质提交
we might have multiple constant buffers, because one might be submitted by the render, or one might be submitted by the material
像往常一样大量的任务，因为游戏引擎相当复杂
huge, huge, huge task as usual, because game engines are quite complicated
我们会慢慢解决这些问题，但我只是想通过展示一个简单的例子来介绍它们
and we'll tackle these things slowly, but I just like to introduce them by showing a simple example
这样那些没有那么有经验的人就不会发现自己经常陷入困境
so that people who aren't as experienced with this won't find themselves in the deep end as often
并且实际上能够理解这个，所以让我们深入到代码中，到处看看，看看能做些什么
and will actually be able to make sense of this, so let's dive into the code and we'll just play around, and see what we can do
好吧，重要的是，如果你们要被这样的东西淹没啦，想想它到底是什么
okay, so the important stuff again is just, if you get overwhelmed with stuff like this, think about what it actually is
正如我之前提到的，这是一堆代码，就是我们的着色器，目前有个顶点和片段着色器
as I've mentioned before, it is a bunch of code, which is our shaders, right, we have a vertex shader and a fragment shader at the moment
我们将其存储在着色器中，Hazel::Shader对象中，那就是所需要的，然后就有了一堆数据
we're storing that in a shader, in a Hazel::Shader object, which is fantastic, that's all we need, and then we have a bunch of data
所以我们现在根本没有用统一变量，不，用到了
so we're not actually using uniforms at all at the moment, oh, no, sorry
我们的顶点着色器用于我们的变换和视图投影矩阵，那都没问题
we are for our vertex shader for our transform and for our view projection matrix, and that's all fine
但我认为，我们从来没有真正在片段着色器中使用过统一变量
but we've never actually used uniform, I think, in the fragment shader
那么首先，就让我们来看看我们的最终目标是什么
so first of all, let's just take a look at what our end goal is
我想做这些，让我们看看，我想做，也许我会做两种不同类型的正方形
I want to make these, let's just see, I want to make, maybe I'll make two different types of squares
所以我们有个正方形的网格，太好了，我希望其中一个是蓝色的，其中一个是红色的
so you saw we had a grid of squares, that's great, I want one of them to be blue, one of them to be red, right
所以我要做的是，也许我们应该把一半做成蓝色，一半做成红色，我不确定
so what I'll do is, so maybe we should make half of them blue, half of them red, I'm not sure
但基本上我要做的是，我要做的第一件事就是找到红色
but basically what I'll do is, the first thing I'll do is find the red
所以我们会有redColor，本质上只是一种颜色，对吧
so we'll have the red color, which will just essentially be a color, right
现在让我们拿我们的蓝色，因为我想做红色，同样的着色器
now let's take our blue color, because I want to make the red color, the same kind of shader
所以我们会快速创建redColor和blueColor，都是vec4，然后这就是blueColor
so we'll make redColor and a blueColor, and it'll be vec4, let's just do this quickly, and then this will be the blueColor
那就是blueColor，然后redColor会是0.8，0.2，0.3，好了，所以我们有两种不同的颜色
that's blueColor, and then the red color will be just 0.8, 0.2, 0.3, okay, so we've got two different colors
我想让，我们可以替换这个
I want to make, we can just literally alternate this
所以我能做的是，我基本上可以看到，if (i % 2) == 0，对吧，所以这只是基本上，应该是x
so what I can do is I can see essentially that if i mod 2 equals 0, right, so this is just basically, sorry it's not i, it's x
所以当我们挨行看时，每一秒钟都等于0，对吧，所以0将是0，1不是0，2将是0等等
so we're kind of, as we go through the rows, every second one will be equal to 0, right, so 0 will be 0, 1 will be not 0, 2 will be 0, etc
我想要做的实际上是设置这个着色器，这个blueShader的统一变量
what I want to do for that is actually set this shader, this blue shader's uniform, which
我不认为，有个UniformMat4，我们会调用UploadUniformFloat4，将其设置为redColor
I don't think we, we have a uniform map4, we'll do UploadUniformFloat4, we'll set this to be the redColor
否则我们会把它设置为blueColor，对吧，所以我们现在有了一个替换模式
and then otherwise we'll set it to be the blueColor, right, so we kind of have an alternate pattern now
现在很明显，这根本没有效率，因为通常你们想把你们的材质批处理
now obviously this is not efficient at all, because usually you would like to batch together your materials
换句话说，你们想尽可能少的做这些
so in other words, you would like to do as few of these as possible
所以我实际上要做的是先渲染所有红色正方形，然后渲染所有蓝色正方形
so what I would actually do is render all the red squares first, then all the blue squares
只是想让每个人都明白，这只是一个测试，我们不是在讨论效率，或者最佳的做事方式
just want everyone to understand, this is just a test, and we're not talking about efficiency, or the optimal way of doing things
但我们基本上是这样做的，最终我们得到了一种交替的颜色模式
but we basically do this, and we end up with an alternating pattern of colors
因此让我们进入Shader类，并确保我们有对应的函数
so let's visit our shader class, and make sure that we have the right function
所以我们会有UploadUniformFloat4，顺便说一下，这个Shader类真的需要一些操作
so we'll have UploadUniformFloat4, this really needs some work by the way, this shader class
所以也许那是接下来要做的，我的意思是，这里有很多事情需要做，我想应该是values
so maybe that's something that I'll do next, because yeah, I mean, there's a lot of stuff that needs to be done here, have values, I guess
我会复制这个，粘贴到这里，我们会像往常一样获取位置
I'll copy this, come over here, paste this in here, we'll get the location as usual
我看到有人评论说缓存位置，那是可以做到的
I saw someone leave a comment about caching the location, yes, that can be done
那不是一种糟糕的方式，这是一种节省性能的快速小把戏
that's not a bad way of just, that's a quick dirty way of just saving some performance
通常，在编译着色器时，通常不会提前计算所有位置
usually you wouldn't, usually you'd calculate all locations ahead of time, when compiling your shader anyway
所以那不是我们真正要的，它是什么，Float4还是UniformVec，到底是什么函数
so that's not something that we're really gonna, what is it, float4 uniform vec, what is the function
我不敢相信我不记得了，就是4f，好了，我们继续，我当然是靠记忆做的
I can't believe I don't remember this, oh, it's just 4, 4v, 4fv, no, 4, 4f, okay, there we go, I'm doing this from memory of course
然后我们就得到了位置，然后是values.x，values.y，values.z和values.w
and then we have the location, and then values x, y, z and w
通常你们基本上只有一个系统，读取着色器
yeah, usually you would, you would basically just have a system, that reads the shader passes
传入着色器，从中获取所有统一变量，然后实际上像获取这些统一变量的位置，就在那里
passes the shader, gets all the uniform values from that, and then actually like gets locations of all of those uniforms, just right there, and then
然后你们那样做，当编译着色器时，就那样，它们被保存了，因为着色器永远不会变，对吧
and then you do that, when compiling your shader, that's it, that's done, they're saved, because the shader is never going to change, right
如果它确实发生了变化，那么你们显然就会重新编译它
if it does change, then you obviously recompile it
这样你们还可以从中获得其他好处，例如验证，确保着色器确实存在
and then that way, you also get other bonus things from that, like validation, making sure the shaders actually exist
这样做，因为你们知道了着色器及其类型，所以就知道缓冲区需要多大
making like, since you're aware of the shaders and their types, you know how much how big your buffer needs to be
这样就可以把它们都存储在缓冲区里，这样就可以继续下去了，所以我们将来会这样做
so that you can store all of them in a buffer, and that kind of just goes on that road, so we'll end up doing that in the future
所以我就叫它u_Color，也就是这个统一变量的名字，好吧，我会把它放在blueShader，对吧
so I'll call this my u_Color, that's going to be the name of this uniform, okay, and I'll just make this inside the blueShader, right
所以蓝色着色器不会是一个平面颜色着色器，实际上会把它重命名为flatColor
so the blue shader is not going to be a flat color shader, and I will actually go as far as to rename it flatColor
所以就明确了它实际上是什么，然后m_BlueShader也是
so there's no confusion as to what it actually is, and then blue shader as well
好了，那么我们如何添加一个统一变量，简单
okay, so how do we add a uniform, simple
我们只需输入uniform，然后类型vec4，然后是统一变量的名称u_Color
we just type in the word uniform, and then the type vec4, and then the name of the uniform u_Color
现在我要做的就是输出color = u_Color，非常简单
and now what I'm going to do is output color to be u_Color, pretty simple
可以使它成为vec3，并保持常量alpha，现在就是1，那很好，但是我们会那样做
could have made this a vec3, and just kept the alpha constant, now it's one as well, that's fine, but we'll do that
也许你们可以下来尝试另一种方式，让我们点击f5，我们应该在我们的方阵中有些不同的
maybe you guys can try the other way at home, let's hit f5, and we should get some kind of difference in our squares
现在有些，一半基本上应该是蓝色的，一半应该是红色的，好了，继续
now some of them, half of them essentially should be blue, half of them should be red, okay, and there you go
所以你们可以看到一半是红色的，一半是蓝色的，那太完美了
so you can see half of them are red and half of them are blue, that's perfect
所以引入了个材质，不是吗，我们就得到了个灵活的着色器，可以添加我们想要的任何颜色
so we've basically introduced a material, haven't we, we've got a shader that is somewhat flexible, we can add any color we want
我们可以很容易添加ImGui来控制改变颜色，有趣，那可能是给你们的作业
we can easily just add an ImGui to control to actually change the color, fun, fact that might be something you guys can do for homework
只需添加ImGui来控制，这样就可以真正玩这个颜色了，我们下期也会做那个
just add an ImGui to control, so that you can actually play around with the color, and we can do that next time as well
但是从本质上讲，我们最终得到的是种方法，可以实际选择所需的颜色并设置到着色器中
but essentially what we end up with is a way to actually pick any color we want and set it into the shader
然后渲染某些东西
and then render something
它将具有该实际值，红色或那个蓝色值，非常酷
and it will be with that actual value, with that red value or with that blue value, which is pretty cool
那一切都很好，但我们基本上从来都不想这样做，对吧
that's all great, but we never want to do this like this way, essentially, right
我们实际上是在取着色器，然后调用UploadUniformFloat4，那有点奇怪
where we actually kind of take the shader, and then we UploadUniformFloat4, that's weird.
相反，我们想要做的是定义某种材质，或多或少在可能看起来像这样的API中
we, instead, what we want to do is define some sort of material, more or less in an API that probably looks like this
我们有Hazel，我可以向你们展示最终目标接口的样子
where we have kind of Hazel and I can show you kind of what a, what a, like an end goal API might look like
因为我们今天绝对不会创建那个
because we're definitely not going to make that today
但是，如果我创建材质，基本上，通常会取Material，可能会是MaterialRef
but if I make a Material, essentially, usually I take a Material, probably have some kind of MaterialRef
因为我们将来会引入某种自动化的引用和计数系统
because we'll introduce some kind of automated kind of reference and counting system in the future
但是现在，由于我们使用的是原始指针或智能指针之类的，所以让我们假装这是个引用
but for now, since we're using kind of raw pointers or smart pointers or whatever, let's just pretend that this is a ref
我想我会向你们展示最终的方法，基本上我们可以创建材质，接收个Shader
I guess I will show you the kind of final way, basically we can just make a material where we take a shader in
所以就是这个flatColorShader，对吧，你们用它做个材质，对吧
so this flatColorShader, right, and you make a material out of that, right
然后通常这样做的实际上就是使用那个着色器
and then what this does is, like typically what this would do is actually take that shader
获取关于着色器需要什么数据的所有信息
get all of the information about what data that shader needs
换句话说，统一变量，特别是适用于实际类似材质的统一变量，对吧
so in other words, the uniforms, specifically the uniforms that are applicable to, to actual like materials, right
例如，正如我之前提到的，如果我们看看这个着色器，决定我想要什么统一变量，对吧
so for example, as I mentioned before, if we look at this shader, and we decide what uniforms do I want, right
我们可以取所有统一变量，那就是三个
yes, we could take all of the uniforms, which would be three
顶点着色器中的这两个，片段着色器中的这一个
it would be these two in the vertex shader, and this one in the fragment shader
虽然不好，因为视图投影矩阵不是，材质的那部分如何，也许有一个变换矩阵
not good though, because a view projection matrix, that is not, how is that part of a material, maybe there is a transfer matrix
所以也许我们把片段着色器中的所有统一变量
so maybe we take all the ones in the fragment shader
在这种情况下，它会起作用，但是如果，我不知道，比如uniform vec3 u_LightDirection
in this case it will work, but what if we have like, I don't know, a uniform, a uniform vec3, you know, u_LightDirection
那有点奇怪，不是吗，我的意思是，为什么光线方向会是材质的一部分
that's a bit weird, isn't it, I mean, why is a light direction part of a material
我总是看到这个，但是当你们设计东西的时候，确保它们有意义，对吧
I see this all the time, but when you're designing things, make sure they make sense, right
比如这只兔子，在这个系列的每期中，我基本上就会拿起来
this bunny here, which I've basically committed to picking up for every episode in this series
这只兔子这儿是什么材质的
this bunny here, this is, what's the material of this
它与光从哪里来有什么关系吗，顺便说一句，不，没有关系
does it have anything to do with, where the light is coming from, which is right there, by the way, no, it doesn't
当然当光线照射到它，它对光有特殊的反应，为什么，因为它有一种材质，对吧
it's just, yeah, sure, the light hits it, it reacts a particular way to the light, why, because it's, well, it's got a material, right
它有某种形式，有个表面属性，它定义就像，你们知道的
it's got some kind of form, it's got a surface property, that defines like, you know
这里就像毛茸茸的一样，实际上感觉很好，但是无论如何，它具有所有那些
it's all like kind of furry here, and actually feels quite nice, but anyway, it kind of, it has all of that
它有一种材质，但它不在乎光从哪里来，那不是材料的一部分，对吧
it's got a material, but it doesn't care where the light's coming from, that's not part of the material, right
我不能，就像改变光线方向不会改变这个兔子制成的材质一样，对吧
I can't, like changing the light direction does not change the material that this bunny is made out of, does it, right
所以只要确保你们在脑子里想清楚事情
so just make sure that you kind of think things through in your head
使用白板或一张纸，如果你们需要记下，问问自己，或者问别人，这个有意义吗
use a whiteboard or a piece of paper, if you need to jot everything down, ask yourself, or ask someone else, does this make sense to you
应该吗，兔子的材质是否包含光线方向，答案是否定的
should it, should the material for the bunny contain the light direction, the answer is no
所以正因为如此，你们不能只是取走所有统一变量，就那样，那就是属于那里的
so because of that, it's again, you can't just take all the uniforms and be like, that's it, that's what belongs there
不，你们需要某种方式来决定渲染器应该设置哪些统一变量
no, you need some kind of way to decide which uniforms should be set by maybe the renderer
所以像渲染器应该设置光线方向，应该设置视图投影，应该设置变换
so like the renderer should set the light direction, should set the view projection, and should set the transform
变换是每个对象的，即使视图投影是每个场景的，光线方向也是如此
transform is kind of per object, even though view projection is per scene, and so is light direction
但是我们还有另一组具体与材质有关的统一变量
but we also have another group of uniforms, which is to do with specifically the material
所以我们需要取那些统一变量，需要创造足够的存储空间
so we need to take those uniforms, and we need to basically create enough storage
就像某种备份缓冲区，它实际上存储了我们需要的所有数据
like some kind of backing buffer, that actually stores all the data that we need
那通常是在创建一种材质时会发生的事情
and that's typically what would happen upon constructing a material
一旦有了那个空间，我们就能做像材质一样的事情
once we have that storage, we can, we'll be able to do things like material, you know
也许只是material->Set()，设置什么，我们想设置材质的颜色，对吧，就是redColor
material, maybe just set, you know, and what are we setting, we want to set the color of the material, right, to be, you know, redColor
就是那样，现在还有材质和材质实例的概念，这就是材质实例
and that's it, now there's also the concept of materials and material instances, which are material instances
本质上只是材质的一个实例，因为你们可能想要定义一个基本材质
that are essentially just an instance of the material, because you might want to define a base material
例如，你们知道的，这个，我不知道，你们知道我的意思
for example, you know, this, I don't, you know what I mean
就像比如创建redColor，因为现在变成了红色材质，不是吗
like instead of making a redColor, because this now becomes a red color material, doesn't it
我是说，就像我把材料的颜色设置为红色，对吧，然后也许我会把它应用到我的网格上
I mean, it's like I've set the materials color to red, right, and then maybe I'll apply it to my mesh
所以我有一个方形的网格，让我们看看，我有个squareMesh，对吧
so I had like a square mesh, let's just see, I had like a squareMesh, right
然后我只是看到，你们知道的，SetMaterial之类的，让我们就用material，对吧
and then I kind of just see, you know, set material or whatever to, let's just say material, right
或者也许我有个覆盖材质，我可以提供给渲染器，即使网格可能有个材质
or, or maybe I have an override material I can supply to the renderer, which says that even though the mesh might have a material
我希望你们覆盖它并设置这个材质，那对于调试和其他类型的渲染情况很有用
I want you to override it and set this material, that's useful for like debugging and also other kinds of rendering cases
但是无论如何，我在这里所做的是我创造了红色材质，太好了，它并不能真正解决任何问题
but anyway, you know, what I've done here is I've created a red material, great, that doesn't really solve anything
所以我可能要做的就是有个平面颜色材质，这个就是
so what I might do is have just a flat color material, which is this
然后从那里，我可能会创建个叫做materialInstance的东西，它是从这个材质派生的
and then from there, I might create something called a materialInstance, which is derived from this material
但是有一组特定的数据，对吧，那不是每个对象唯一之类的
but has a specific set of data, right, that isn't kind of that is unique per object or something like that
所以另一个例子可能是，可能是，我有一种基于物理的渲染金属材质，就像银，对吧
so another example might be, might be, I have a kind of physically based rendering metal material, that's like silver, right
那可能是我的基础材质，但是我渲染的不同球体可能具有不同的粗糙度，或者可能有点破损
that might be my base material, but different spheres that I render might have different roughness, or they might be a bit damaged
所以它们可能有不同的粗糙度或类似映射的镜面
so they might have a different like roughness or like specularity kind of like map, essentially
就像你们应用的纹理一样，它决定了球体的某些部分看起来有点破旧，对吧
like a texture that you apply that determines certain parts of the sphere look a bit beaten up, right
那就像是个材质实例，因为基础材质是银
that would be like a material instance, because the base material is silver
就像你们创造的那种银色PBR材质
it's like that kind of, you know, the silver PBR material that you've created
但是派生的可能有一些特殊的东西使得它独一无二
but then the derived one might have a few kind of particular things, that makes it unique
因为很明显，你们不会经常渲染一个充满所有完全相同形状的场景
because obviously you wouldn't often render a scene filled with everything that is exactly in the same shape
但有可能是相同的材质，在你们的场景中可能有很多木头，对吧
it might be the same material, it might be a lot of wood in your scene, right
但它，你们知道的，很可能是不同类型的木材，或者质量不同，比如可能有点退变之类的
but it, you know, it's likely that it's different types of wood or it's different like qualities, like it might be a bit degraded or whatever
所以我们最终得到了一个有点像这样的接口
so we kind of end up with an API that somewhat looks like this
这是我实际上在私有分支所做的事情，可供赞助人使用
and it's something that I've actually done in the private branch, that's available to patrons
顺便说一句，非常感谢所有使该系列成为可能的赞助人，patreon.com/thecherno
by the way, huge thank you to all the patrons that make this series possible, patreon.com/thecherno
这些东西已经在那里完成了，所以我已经测试了这段代码，如果你们现在想看的话
yeah, this stuff has already been done there, so I've kind of tested this code, and if you want to see it right now
你们可以帮助支持这个系列，就可以访问这些代码
you can just help support the series, and you'll get access to all this lovely code
但是无论如何，回到这，所以已经完成了，但是本质上讲，可能会有MaterialInstanceRef
but anyway, back to this, so I kind of have done this already, but essentially you might have like a MaterialInstanceRef
就像你们知道的，materialInstance
which would be like your actual, you know, materialInstance
这只是，你们知道的，同样的事情，我们有一个Hazel::MaterialInstance(material)
this would just be, you know, the same kind of thing where we have a Hazel::MaterialInstance, made from a material
然后我们可以为特定的材质设置某些类似的颜色，对吧，但就是那样
and then we can set certain like colors to that specific material, right, but that's kind of it
然后你们最终会用一个特定的材质实例渲染些东西
and then you end up with rendering something with a particular material instance
在这个例子中，你们不需要UploadUniformFloat4之类的，因为已经这样做了那个
and in this example, you know, you don't need to UploadUniformFloat4 or whatever, because you've already done that
相反，如果我暂时注释这段代码，我们会继续，也许会提交一些东西
we would instead, if I just kind of get rid of this code for now, we would instead go ahead and maybe submit something
不再使用着色器，我们会提交带有特定材质的东西
we wouldn't use a shader anymore, we'd submit something with a particular material
然后那个材质要做的就是取决于我们在Renderer::Submit中绑定那个材质
and then what that material would do is upon us binding that material inside Renderer::Submit
它不希望渲染器做这些东西，但最终我们基本上，我们找到了着色器，很好
it wouldn't like the renderer does this stuff, that's fine, but ultimately we basically, we find, we find the shader, and that's fine
那都是需要的，必要的
that's all needed, that's all necessary
但是对我们来说，下一步是实际获取该材质实例并将其绑定
but then the next step for us would be to actually take that material instance and bind it
通过实现那个，它将绑定着色器并设置所有值
and by doing that, what that does is it binds the shader and sets all of the values
它设置了我们实际存储的所有数据，也就是那个MaterialInstance
that sets all of the data that we've actually are storing is that MaterialInstance
那就像，那太棒了，整个系统，很棒，你们真的可以扩展它
and that's like, that's just fantastic, that whole kind of system, it's great, you can really extend it
你们可以让它变得非常强大
you can make it really powerful
我甚至可能不打算这样做，但是我可以证明，也许下期，这种东西会有用，我不确定
I might even like I don't wasn't planning on doing this, but I could show, maybe next time, this stuff kind of working, I'm not sure
有时我不确定解释其中一些事情的最佳方法是什么
sometimes I'm not sure what the best way to explain some of these things are
我绝对想用一种正式的方式来做这件事，比如你们知道的，绘制图表之类的
and I definitely want to kind of do this in more of like a formal way of like, you know, drawing diagrams and stuff
我认为那很重要，但是当我们在引擎中进入更复杂的主题时，有时有一个例子是很好的
I think that's kind of important, but as we get into more complex topics in the engine, sometimes it's good to have an example
我试着用一些伪代码为你们做这件事，但也会写代码
and I've tried to kind of do that for you with somewhat pseudocode, but also code that
看起来与我们正在努力的最终接口非常相似
looks very similar to the final API that we're kind of working towards
但最终，你们会有些不同的，所以我可能会给你们看些开发分支的东西
but ultimately, you know, you have kind of different like, so I might show you some of the development branch stuff
因为材质实例和材质，所有这些东西对于让它正常和快速地运行都是至关重要的
because, you know, material instances, materials, all that stuff have been kind of vital to get that to work properly And quickly as well
因为同样，一旦你们有一堆使用不同材质渲染的对象
because again, once you have a bunch of objects that you render with different materials
你们最终能够把它们批处理，你们知道的
you end up kind of being able to batch them together, you know
这样你们就可以从本质上做一些渲染排序，这样就可以得到所有的红色方块
so that you kind of do some render sorting essentially, so that you get all of like the red squares
就像我这里说的，然后是所有的原因是因为红色方形具有红色的材质实例
as I said, here and then all of the why, because the red squares have the red MaterialInstance
因此，让我们知道，当我们将所有内容提交给渲染时，因为渲染程序
so let's, you know, when we submit everything to the render, since to the renderer
因为我们不会一次渲染所有内容，假设在一个好的渲染器中，我们拥有所有的数据
since we don't render everything at once, you know, hypothetically in a good renderer, we have all that data
然后到了排序的时候，我们可以看到，好吧，所有红色的东西都会先渲染
and then when it comes time to sort it, we can see, okay, well, everything that's red will render first
所有蓝色的东西都会渲染第二个，这样我们只绑定两个材质，对吧
everything that's blue will render second, that way we only bind two materials, right
我们绑定红色材质，用它渲染所有东西，绑定蓝色材质，用它渲染所有东西
we bind the red material, render everything with it, bind the blue material, render everything with it
显然，仍然需要设置某些着色器属性 (例如变换)，那完全没问题
obviously certain shader properties like the transform still needs to be set, that's fine
但至少我们不是每次想要渲染其中一个正方形时都设置颜色，因为渲染的是400正方形
but at least we're not setting the color every time, every time we want to render one of these squares, because we are rendering 400 squares
我们做了400次材质翻转，那会比做更少需要更长的时间
we did 400 material flips, that's going to take way longer than doing less
无论如何，我认为那可能就是我想向你们展示的东西了
anyway, I think that's probably about it in terms of what I wanted to show you guys
但是，如果我们只是跳回到这里，纹理的原理相同，对吧，我的意思是，比如SetTexture()
if we just jump back here for a sec, though, textures work the same way, right, I mean, you could make like a SetTexture
你们不一定要，因为我们还没有处理纹理，那是我们真正需要做的事情
you don't necessarily have to, we haven't dealt with textures yet, that's something that we really need to do
但如果我们有个纹理类，就像我们可能有纹理一样，我们可能有反射贴图之类的
but you know, if we had a texture or something like that, like we might have texture, we might have like an albedo map or something
我们基本上可以通过上传纹理引用之类的的方式来设置
we can just set that basically by just uploading a texture reference or something like that in kind of the same way
或者可以更明确一点，这样你们就知道实际上在做什么，像SetTexture一样
or you could be a bit more explicit, so that you know what you're actually doing and do like SetTexture
也许你们就有SetTexture，或者SetValue，可以根据自己的风格设计这个接口
and maybe you have SetTexture, SetValue, you can design this API however you like
但本质上，它对纹理的运行方式一样
but essentially, it works the same way for textures
材质或材质实例将存储一大堆基本上对纹理的引用
and the material or the MaterialInstance would store a whole bunch of references essentially to textures
然后我们基本上可以渲染具有特定纹理的东西，因此它是一个非常不错的系统
and then we could basically render something with a particular texture, so it's a really nice system
我真的很喜欢材质系统的整个概念
I really like the whole concept of material systems
我一直很喜欢它，因为它太神奇了，实际上给了你们很多安全感
I've always kind of liked it, because it's amazing, how much safety it actually gives you
在某种程度上，几乎就像智能指针，你们可以上传统一变量
it's almost like smart pointers in a way, you could just upload uniforms
你们会看到第一次学习OpenGL或学习图形编程的人，他们在做什么
you look at kind of people learning OpenGL for the first time, or graphics programming for the first time, what are they doing
通常他们创建一个着色器，他们可能会足够聪明来创建个着色器类之类的
usually they create a shader, they'll be probably smart enough to create a shader class or something like that
然后是一个让他们设置变量和设置统一变量的接口
and then an API that lets them set variables and set uniforms
他们可以做一些基本上最终验证的东西，确保统一变量的存在
and they can make something essentially that ends up validating that, making sure stuff exists
如果位置等于-1，意味着没有统一变量，他们会记录它，或者在那里断言，以便可以调试
maybe if location equals -1, which means the uniform couldn't be found, they log that, or they assert there so they can debug it
太好了
that's all great
但是有材质系统，像一个合适的系统，在那里可以问着色器，嘿，把所有的统一变量给我
but having a material system where you can actually, like a proper one, where you can ask the shader, hey, give me all of your uniforms
占用这么多空间，我可以将它们存储在缓冲区中，然后在需要时将其上传
okay, occupy this much space, okay, I can store them in a buffer, and then upload them when needed
或者我可以有个材质实例，用这个或那个覆盖该缓冲区
or I can have a material instance, which overrides that buffer and says this, this and that or whatever
这太神奇了，因为如果你们写得正确，这一切都不会出错
it's just amazing, because nothing will ever kind of go wrong with this, if you write it properly
显然，那就是我们要做的，所以对此感到非常兴奋
that's what we're going to do, obviously, so yeah, super excited for that
我们需要，在我们真正做到这一点之前，我们真的需要创建着色器类
we need to, before we can actually do this, though, we really do need to build up our Shader class a little bit more
我的意思是，我们现在甚至不能从文件中读取着色器，所以那绝对是我想做的事情
I mean, we can't even read shaders from files at the moment, so that's kind of definitely something that I want to do
我要问你们个重要的问题，已经问过了，但是我现在要正式问这个问题，所以听好了
the other huge question that I have for you guys, and I have asked that, but I'm going to ask it formally right now, so listen up
我们现在是否要继续使Hazel成为完整的3D渲染器，还是要更多地关注2D
do we want to proceed with making Hazel a full 3D renderer right now, or do we want to focus more on 2D
同样，材质较少，对2D非常有用，因为通常你们会在2D场景中渲染几乎所有内容
again, materials less, so useful for 2D, because usually you would render pretty much everything in a 2D scene
除了像特殊效果或特殊的东西，只有一个着色器，所以你们真的不需要太多的材质
aside from like special effects or special things with just a single shader, so you don't really need too many materials
你们可以只有一个2D渲染器，它基本上渲染颜色或纹理和形状，那就是你们所需要的
you can just have a 2D renderer, which basically renders colors or textures and shapes, that's all you need
所以它会把这些东西放在后面，很好
so it will kind of put this stuff on the back burner, which is fine
无论哪种方式，我们仍然需要重新访问着色器类，并且仍然需要100% 重新访问纹理
either way, we still need to revisit our shader class, and we still need to 100% revisit textures
所以接下来我可能会做其中的一期，但真正的问题是，我要做个投票
so I'll probably do one of those episodes next, but the real question is, and I'm going to make a poll
上次我做了一个投票，我真的不太喜欢它，因为我不知道如何正确地看到结果
last time I made a poll, I didn't really like it too much, because I don't know how to see the results properly
上次我在投票中看到结果的方式是我自己看了视频，投了票，然后看到了百分比是多少
the way I saw the results on my own poll last time was I watched the video myself, voted for something, then saw what the percentages were
我不知道有多少人投票，对此我一无所知，也许我应该更多地使用Google，但似乎很奇怪
I don't know how many people voted, I don't know anything about it, I should probably Google more maybe, but it just seems weird
我甚至无法在分析中看到它，所以有点奇怪，但我将再次进行投票
I couldn't even see it in my analytics, so it was a bit weird, but I'll make a poll once again
你们是否想进入2D方向并做出很酷的事情，例如快速的2D渲染器
do you guys want to be going to 2D direction and make a cool, like blazing fast 2D renderer
让Hazel现在基本上可以制作2D游戏，然后把它润色，做好准备
and just make Hazel able to make 2D games basically right now and just polish that up, make it ready to go
或者我们应该花更长的时间来制作3D渲染器，无论哪种方式，都将进行2D，然后继续3D
or should we take a lot longer and make a 3D Renderer, either way, we're going to do 2D and then move on to 3D
无论哪种方式，内容都会在那里
the content will be there either way
显然，我对3D充满热情，并且我想制作一个非常好的3D渲染器和一个好的3D游戏引擎
obviously I'm very passionate about 3D, and I want to actually make a very good 3D Renderer and a good 3D game engine
所以不管怎样，它都会支持两者，我不可能忽视它
so either way, it's going to support both, there's no way I neglect it
先做2D可能更有意义，只要它完成了
might make more sense to do 2D first, just so that it's finished
你们实际上可以开始用Hazel制作游戏，看到它可以作为游戏引擎运行，那将是非常酷的
and you guys can actually start making games with Hazel and seeing it actually work as a game engine, I think that would be very cool
显然，与适当的3D渲染器相比，它将花费更少的时间，因此那样做可能更有意义
and obviously it's going to take less time, a lot less time than a proper 3D Renderer, so it might make more sense to do that
但是不管怎样，顺便说一句，我将继续OpenGL系列，所以你们会在那里看到3D的东西
but either way, and I am going to continue the OpenGL series, by the way, so you'll see 3D stuff there
所以，如果你们担心在接下来的六个月里，这个频道现在根本不是3D频道
so if you're worried about just this channel being not 3D at all now for the next six months
不用担心，因为无论哪种方式，我们肯定会继续OpenGL系列中的3D内容
don't worry about that, because definitely we'll be continuing 3D stuff in the OpenGL series for sure, either way
但是如果你们想要2D或3D，让我知道
but if you want that, if you want 2D or 3D, let me know
在投票中投票，我下次会看结果，并可能确定我们的方向
vote in the poll, and I'll check the results next time, and probably determine where we're going
但是无论哪种方式，我们都在做着色器，所以不用担心
but either way, we're doing the shader, so don't worry about that
无论如何，我希望你们喜欢这期视频，如果喜欢的话，就为它点赞吧
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video, if you did, please hit the like button
正如我前面提到的，patreon.com/thecherno是帮助支持本系列的最佳网址
as I mentioned earlier, patreon.com/thecherno is the best place to help support this series
感谢所有让这个系列成为可能的人，下次见，拜
thank you to all of you people who make this series possible, I will see you next time, goodbye